Cameron Rutherford HPC/ML/Q Research Software Engineer

 Manhattan, NY
 ✓ cameron.rutherford@me.com
 ☐ (509) 218-1818

• cameronrutherford in Robert C Rutherford

Summary

High Performance Computing (HPC) / Machine Learning (ML) / Quantum (Q) Research Software Engineer (RSE) with over 3 years of experience deploying, testing, optimizing and teaching people about scientific software and computing systems. I have worked on a wide variety of projects during my time at "the lab", and have had my code run on everywhere from the largest supercomputer in the world, to a novel quantum computer.

Skills

C / C++17	Python	DevOps
CMake, Spack, CUDA / HIP	Pytorch, JAX, Distributed ML	Docker, ghcr, S3
RAJA + Umpire / Kokkos	conda, poetry, mamba	Singularity/Apptainer, charliecloud, podman
MPI, pybind11, toml11, spdl	og quarto, nbdev, qiskit	GitHub, GitLab, pre-commit

Experience

Software Engineer HPC/ML/	, Pacific Northwest National Laboratory (Virtual)	2020 - Present
---------------------------	---	----------------

- test
- test
- test

Sports Events Coordinator, Whitworth University (Spokane, WA)	2019 - 2020
IT Intern, Mac Management, Keysight Technologies (Colorado Springs, CO)	2018
Calculus III Grader / Mathematics Tutor, Whitworth University (Spokane, WA)	2017, 2019
Basketball Coach, S.G.S. & M.L.C (Sydney, AUS)	2015

Publications

- S. Abhyankar, S. Peles, R. Rutherford, A. Mancinelli, Evaluation of AC optimal power flow on graphical processing units. (IEEE PESGM 2021)
- S. Peles, M. Alam, A. J. Mancinelli, K. Perumalla, R. C. Rutherford, J. Ryan, C. G. Petra, Porting the Nonlinear Optimization Library HiOp to Accelerator-Based Hardware Architectures (arxiv 2021)

Conferences

Practice and Experience in Advanced Research Computing (PEARC)	2023
Pacific Northwest National Laboratory (PNNL) Tech Fest	2021-2023
Energy Exascale Earth System Model (E3SM) Annual Meeting	2023
Sustainable Tools Ecosystem Project (STEP) East Coast Town Hall	2023
Exascale Computing Project (ECP) Annual Meeting	2021-2023
Pacific Northwest National Laboratory (PNNL) Innovation Summit	2022
Co-Design Centre for Quantum Advantage (C2QA) Annual Meeting	2022
Education	
Scientist & Engineer Rising Leader Learning Journey	2023
Cyber Security & National Security Seminar Series, PNNL	2021 - 2022

G.P.A 3.9/4.0

Outstanding Mathematics Major 2020

Whitworth University, B.S. Mathematics and Computer Science

- ICPC Pacific Northwest Eastern Washington Site Winner 2018
 Howard R. Gage Memorial Scholarship 2017, 2018, 2019

Other Activities

Sustainable Horizons Institute HPC Mentor	2022, 2023
Quantum Information Science / HPC STEM Mentor	2022 - Present
Whitworth Chess Club President	2019 - 2020
Pine Codes Hackathon Winner	2019
SpokAnimal Shelter Volunteer	2019
Whitworth Men's Basketball Team	2016 - 2019